this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
PC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Dave cross
Dave has been programming professionally
since 1988.
and a pearl user for a very long time I
actually came across Dave in 2010 when I
was a big pearl Catalyst user
he is the author of data mugging with
pearl from Manning and a co-author of
pearl template toolkit from O'Reilly
Dave runs and Owens Magnum Solutions and
open source development consultancy
based in London
his latest book is called GitHub actions
from Clapham technical press hey welcome
to software engineering radio is there
anything I missed that you'd like to add
hi thank you for having me no just to
emphasize what you said about my career
starting in 1988 which means I am very
old and the fact that I'm
enthusiastic about some of these newer
Technologies is because so much of my
career was spent without them so you've
seen them before whereas manual and
everything will absolutely this is so
much easier excellent perfect
so we're gonna have a chat about
obviously the shows about GitHub actions
we're going to talk about the value
they've provided and discuss an example
project that implements the main parts
of continuous integration and continuous
deployment with a few surprises along
the way out so let's get started
continuous integration and continuous
deployment let's start with the basics
Dave what is CI
so CI it's automating the bits of your
project which mean that you can measure
the quality of your project I guess it
means that every time you commit some
new code to your code base or changed
code into your code base you can run
processes which do things like run unit
tests run a linter against your code
base and perform other quality metrics
like maybe measuring the complexity of
the code or the coverage of your tests
that kind of thing the kind of numbers
that might end up on a dashboard that is
on a monitor hanging above the
development team so that everyone who
walks past the team can see how good
your code is if you were to come across
a new project on GitHub or your
recommended one what would be the first
thing you'd look at to see what the
continuous integration would be I think
the first thing that I would be looking
at is the coverage
just to see how well the test Suite
matches the amount of code that you've
actually got in the project having a
test Suite that covers the code base
well means that you have more it's
easier to change code and know that
you're not breaking things yeah it gives
you that safety net doesn't it and
obviously you'd want there to be some
type of integration in the project yes
yeah so that would be the first thing
hopefully what is continuous deployment
so that's the step that comes after
continuous integration it means that
once you are happy that your code is
good or even better than it was
previously then you can automatically
take that code from your GitHub server
or whatever Source Code system you're
using and move it into production in a
manner that is easy to reproduce so
hopefully just pressing a button and at
the end of some processes running the
code is up on your production server and
running
excellent thank you for the listeners
who want to get into cicd continuous
integration contingent deployment more
we've actually done a full show on it
which was 0498 with James so call on
continuous integration and continuous
delivery moved on episode 554 on
behavioral code analysis which is really
good episode five four four four eight
two four forty four two four and an
older one and continuous Delivery
episode 221 I'll put those links in the
show notes but it helps expand on this
very light overview I've just done with
Dave so before I move on to the core of
the the show which is GitHub actions is
there a sort of low hanging fruit to put
into CI there's a safety net and
something in CD or does it depend on the
project and you know the software
developer to a large extent I guess it
does depend on the project but as I said
earlier I think getting your unit tests
running in some kind of CIA framework is
very useful excellent there's simple
things on GitHub like
I suppose it depends on the project like
the depends thing or what's there static
analysis one code ql I think it is yes
yeah yeah and there's things that do
things like looking for
secret books and things like that yeah
depends on what you've got in your
project I suppose
yeah yeah excellent thank you right
so now we're gonna dig into GitHub
actions most of the show will be spent
between this section and the example
project please bear with us so Dave what
is or are GitHub actions so GitHub
action to just I was trying to trying to
work out when it was that GitHub actions
was introduced I reckon it's about a
couple of years old and listeners may
have come across product like Jenkins or
Travis Ci or or Circle CI which many
projects or many of my clients are using
to do CI and CD GitHub actions is
github's answer to that it allows you to
Define
workflows and the definition of those
workflows actually sit within your code
repo and then in response to various
events GitHub will fire up a container
and run through the steps in your
process which allows you to do CI and CD
but it isn't limited to that and as
we'll I'm sure mention later there are
plenty of other things that you can do
with it yeah I think for a long time
GitHub as it was GitHub will before
Microsoft there wasn't any GitHub action
so you had to use one of those and then
they were quite late to the game weren't
they yes yes various reasons but they I
guess they counted that by coming up
with something that is more powerful
than Jenkins or Travis CI because as I
say it's not just limited to CI and CD
yeah exactly and you mentioned there
that it does Things based on certain
events would that be solely defined as
an event driven architecture yes it's an
event driven architecture but I suppose
you need to be quite liberal in your
definition of what an event is because
it's event driven to the extent that you
can trigger
your your workflow to run
when something is pushed to your code
base when you get a pull request to your
code base when someone raises an issue
in your code base all these kinds of
obvious source code control events
but there are other things it basically
gives you a complete Cron job
implementation you can trigger events
trigger workflows on time purely you can
trigger workflows manually you can get a
button on the workflow page and say just
run this now or the other thing you can
do is basically use it as a web hook so
you can just make an HTTP request GitHub
and it will trigger your workflow so
there's plenty of different ways of
running a workflow yes brilliant one I
wasn't aware of is that web hook auction
yeah and I'd like to explore with you I
think it's on the agenda when somebody
raises an issue as well what you can do
with that okay perfect so I presume the
owner of the project needs to create
some type of definition of what they
want to happen with GitHub actions can
you take me through what that looks like
yeah so inside your repo GitHub have
defined this now a DOT GitHub directory
which you can create and that's where
GitHub specific files go one example is
you mentioned earlier dependable and you
can put a yaml file in there
dependable.yaml and that finds what kind
of pendable interactions you want but
also within that dot GitHub directory is
a workflows directory and inside there
you can create as many yaml files as you
like and each of those is a workflow
definition So within a workflow
definition there are a number of steps
there's kind of a header which gives the
workflow a name tells it what
architecture you want it to run on and I
guess we'll come back to that in more
detail a bit later on and then there's a
number of jobs which Define the code and
jobs can be broken down into individual
steps and each individual step is a
piece of code that you want to run
so that's kind of the high level look at
what a workflow definition looks like
and before I move on to the next
question those I don't know what depend
about is I supposed to be about to
Define it do you want to have a go Dave
yeah so dependable is a I'm not sure
whether it comes from GitHub or whether
they've brought it in from another
company it does a number of things the
thing when I first saw it was when I
started having some GitHub Pages
websites within my repos that were
generated using various node
applications
and dependable would come along every
once in a while and check dependencies
within my node applications and make
sure that I wasn't running versions that
had known security leaks and it wouldn't
just check and give me a warning it
would actually produce a pull request
which fixes the problem by bringing the
dependency up to a known good version it
works in a number of different
ecosystems checking for outdated
dependencies that have security issues
thanks so just to summarize GitHub has
some predefined things it wants to see
and it's project repository which would
be on your faster system it would look
like a hidden folder but it's actually
dot GitHub GitHub specific things live
in there depending on what you're trying
to do but in general there's a workflows
as it flows workflows directory yes yeah
and then inside there anything that is a
does it have to be a DOT yml file yaml
file or I think so yeah I've never tried
putting anything else there but yeah me
either so anything in there that a
comparison figure out it would generally
show up under the actions tab on the
GitHub project that's right yes and just
to touch on the event driven thing I
presume you can go to the actions tab on
your project and click go to run
something yeah so I talked about there
being a kind of header section in the
workflow definition file one of the
options there is name as I mentioned but
the most important one is on just on and
that defines how your workflow is
triggered and so it would be a list of
different ways that you want it to
trigger on a pull request on a push and
one of those is a special value called
workflow batch and I can never remember
whether it's an underscore or a dash but
if you've got on workflow match in your
work flow definition file then when you
go to the page for that action in your
repo there will be a button that just
says run action or run workflow so you
just push that you could and it runs it
use that to actually go to production so
it's not automated there's someone else
to push it yes yes I didn't know that
excellent can the actions
use Docker images or otherwise how do
the actions get the binaries they need
you know as in that's your project being
built into a binary or libraries it
needs or something so the actions all
run on containers on Docker containers
GitHub Supply some of their own standard
containers and there are ones for
various popular operating systems they
will do
some light enhancements to them for
example they will install the GitHub
command line package so you've got
access to that so without doing anything
clever it will just run on a pretty
standard operating system
container but you are perfectly
able to find your own container so if
you are using one of the GitHub
containers then as you hint at problem
is you need to install all the software
that you need in order to run your
processes
so it's often a good idea to Define your
own container that's got the software
already installed you can store that on
any of the popular container
repositories so you can put it up on the
docker hub for example and then in the
header of your workflow definition you
would say this runs on
and and then give it the part to your
Docker container and then when the
workflow is triggered GitHub would pull
that container down and start it up so
you've already got all the software
installed yeah that's a good point
because I normally just run as if I'm
setting a Debian or Ubuntu machine
or the app get to install the different
things I need but if I did my own
container and pushed that to Docker Hub
or some other place I could just pull
that down and really reduce some of my
time it takes to run yeah this is
actually this is something that I've
done quite a lot of recently because I
had some actions whose job was generate
static web pages that were powered that
were run in GitHub pages and it was
using a module a Perl module that was
being installed on every run and it was
taking five minutes to get the container
ready in order to run the software that
builds the website so I just spent a
couple of hours putting together a
container that had all the software
installed and now these workflows run in
a minute or something rather than seven
minutes yeah I suppose it's a trade-off
between you keeping your own container
up to date you know and yes now you've
got one more thing to look after and at
least well if there's no time constraint
suppose I know GitHub does been off some
long things or you can set how long it
runs for yes it does the opportunity
Flex the install process and make sure
it's always working I suppose depending
on what your project is but isn't there
the concept of a when I see that lately
yeah for one of the deployment things
that I use all right and Docker in
general it's got the build image doesn't
it just GitHub actions have the similar
concept so cash is the last build for
you yes the honest answer is I don't
know I've never noticed it because these
websites that I was talking about
building it was building everything from
scratch every time maybe that was just
because I hadn't turned the cache on
okay perhaps but basically I guess I'm
using the docker Harbors or cash yeah
it's a similar thing I'll put some links
in the show notes if I can find
something anyway these actions can you
reuse them let's just go back to the
word two words GitHub actions and action
is the workflow definition isn't it
well to be honest I think GitHub have
blindly muddied the water here GitHub
actions is what they call this entire
feature but when they are talking about
setting up a workflow they are very
careful to call it a workflow definition
file so your yaml file is a workflow
definition file the meet this definition
file as I said there's a number of jobs
which are broken down into steps and now
each step is either a piece of code that
you can run so basically a piece of bash
code that runs as though you were typing
it on the command line on your Ubuntu
container or it's what they call an
action which is kind of an overloading
of the term because in this case an
action is a reusable piece of code that
people can make available for your use
in your workflows by putting it in a
special format on GitHub so actions
really has two slightly different
meanings in the the GitHub Eco system
but what actions really are it's almost
like a library it's a reusable piece of
code that you can slot into your steps
in your workflow definition yeah it's
just when I asked that question that
sort of modeled in my head yes so and
that's completely understandable and
just a summary GitHub actions is like
their product name yes the workflow
definition that we're in control offers
what sits in our project yeah and then
if we want to shrink our workflow file
or do something complicated or just you
know use something that's used by other
people the actual word actions is what
they call
the reusable blocks I can call in your
workflow file exactly to do something
yes you might not be able to do or you
know it saves you time because you have
to think about it for example the most
commonly used action the action that is
used in pretty much every workflow file
ever is called action slash checkout
and you use that as one of the steps one
of the first steps in your workflow
definition file and that will check out
the code of your repo onto the container
and the container definition be
something like Ubuntu Windows Mac
depending on what version you want to
change on correct no architecture okay
so I think we've defined the product of
actions the workflow what a workflow
file looks like those of us that have
used answerable it's kind of similar and
kind of looks like a Docker file as well
which we've done shows on the action's
reusable because it's a separate Library
as it were the access model because
we're using a darker container where is
that container living is that a root
user is what does it have access to the
thing that's running the code so there's
a number of different levels to this as
to where the container runs I think
GitHub really want you to think about it
in the same way as you would think about
a serverless implementation in AWS you
don't care about where the server is
running it's just running on a container
that is running on one of github's
pieces of Hardware somewhere in the
world I haven't come across anything
like areas that AWS have you can't say
you want it to run in that part of the
world or anything like that it's just a
container that's running somewhere in
the world the next level is that you are
running as a user on that container and
on the GitHub standard containers that
they give you you will be straight in
there as root obviously if you're
building your own container then that
might have different setups one
confusion that I sometimes get is
switching between a GitHub container and
a container that I've developed myself
is that the GitHub container like I said
puts you in as root and then I switch to
what my own container and you're no
longer root so you have to sudo when you
want to install and every time I make
that switch it catches me out and you'll
see a couple of commits when I'm fixing
whether I need to add a sudo or take
away a sudo command if you're not
running as root you're running as a user
that has access to root through sudo but
that's common enough within a container
I guess and then the third level is how
is that user what permissions does that
have on your GitHub repo and the answer
is it basically runs as the person that
owns the repo where it is hosted where
the workflow definition file lives you
have part of the environment that GitHub
workflow sets up for you you have an
environment variable effectively it's
not quite an environment variable called
GitHub token which has access to the
permissions that the owner of the repo
has to the repo which are by default
going to be all read and write access to
the repo but you can add a permissions
definition both at the job level and
also at the individual step level to
change the permissions that the workflow
has to your Reaper
so you can cut back the permissions so
you can't accidentally write to things
that you don't want to write to for
example when you go to the settings of a
GitHub project and you've got multiple
collaborators or team members that you
might have assigned different role to or
access that was it's the GitHub
repository owner that is
the permission set that is used running
the actions but then of course depending
on what's happened I mean if you Fork a
repo then the fork is obviously owned by
a different person so they have that so
it's the book includes the workflow
definition files but they will only have
permissions on their Fork of the repo
rather than your main copy of the repo
so if you've got any secret definitions
which we'll talk on because you're
pulling some other repo or you know
you're pushing somewhere that needs an
SSH key or something like that the fork
obviously wouldn't have access to that
environment so some jobs May Fail yes
but that would be good probably I've not
been in this situation myself where I've
had to think of that level of
granularity for running bits of a
workflow with different emission levels
so that's good to know thank you so this
state as in the GitHub that they offer
cross-platform support yes what does
that mean so it means that the GitHub
supplied Runners the containers that
we've talked about before they are
available basically in three different
flavors there is a Ubuntu flavor there
is a Windows flavor and there is a Macos
flavor and for each of those there are
some different versions available I'm
not entirely sure how far back those
versions go so when you set up a
workflow definition you say what it runs
on one of the things you can do the one
of the easiest ways to get a workflow up
and running is just to say that it runs
on Ubuntu and they will just pull down
the the latest version of their lightly
modified Ubuntu container and you can
run it on there but they also work for
Windows and Macos of course because you
can run your own containers too there's
nothing to stop you running on a
container that runs a completely
different OS so if you're not defining
Ubuntu data latest or Mac OS latest
whatever would you put in in that line
Docker image you want to pull or you or
are you running your own Docker image
inside Ubuntu no no you run it instead
so yes the runs on is either one of
their label for their own containers or
definition of your own container okay
because I've seen myself
mess up Docker on my workstation here
which is a fedora one I've then used
virtualbox to run a Debian thing and
then run Docker inside that so I thought
it was something like that no I don't
believe so no I've personally been
caught this week and last week on a
couple of the projects when I use Ubuntu
latest or Mac OS latest or something and
I've had to go back to a fixed version
because they've changed what the latest
tag is yes
and then all the libraries you depend on
or different environmental variables or
the bundled version of python or
Homebrew or something that's changed and
all your stuff takes so yeah I can
understand that what they will do is if
you go to the beach action or each
workflow to be accurate and each run of
that workflow has a page on your repo
and so if you go to that workflow when
those changes are imminent there will be
a notice that appears quite clearly at
the bottom of that page saying you are
using Ubuntu latest in three weeks time
that will go from being
22.04 to 23.04 or something like that so
they do try to pass that information on
but yes if you're I didn't know yeah
because I had to rule something back
last week but obviously if you want to
be really careful about the version that
you're using then yeah you will want to
give version number rather than late
it's a tricky one because it's flexing
your software on a different version of
platform so it's kind of good in a way
but it's noise because you haven't
changed any of your code potentially yes
but then presumably the people that are
using your software will be updating
their OS at some point so you do want to
know about those breakages yeah exactly
similar when it's an open source project
you just don't want that red icon on
your exactly project either so it gives
you the old broken windows yeah
philosophy so do you have any concept of
how scale scalable and performant GitHub
actions are in your experience I'm not
really sure in what way it needs to be
scalable are you picturing a repo that
fires off events every few seconds that
start running a workflow I'm thinking
about maybe this is just a case of
putting a link into the available images
that GitHub haven't how many CPUs they
give to a container and how much RAM you
know say you've got a really Ram heavy
project yes will that run or you know
will you have to pay more to get that or
will it just take 30 minutes instead of
yeah I'm to be honest I'm not sure what
size the containers are that they're
running okay I'll dig that out for
people that want to study performance
well we've already talked earlier about
the speed up that I got from switching
from using one of their containers to
using a container that I built myself
that had already got the software
installed on it the other thing that you
can think about there is you can control
what the workflow does when things fail
you might want failed as quickly as
possible if something goes wrong then
there's no point in carrying on so you
can make things maybe not faster but
stop running
sooner so you get the results quicker by
controlling the error flow yeah and that
gives you a good indication if
something you've done is taken too long
you can set it to bail out as well yeah
and you can also as you mentioned
earlier there's time out and I think the
volt timeout is something like three
minutes but you can bring that in if you
want perfect thanks I think we've
mentioned it a couple of times but if
you want to store password for Secrets
as the general term credentials in there
because you have to go and fetch
something or
push something out and your continuous
deployment yes
how did you go about that so if you go
to the settings in your repo you will
find that there is a secret item on the
menu and you can go in there and you can
fill in secrets that are just key value
Pairs and I'm no security expert but
GitHub tell us that that information is
stored in very secure manner on their
servers obviously it has to be a
reversible encryption so that you can
then get access to the values so that
they can use them but they exist at
three different levels you can have
secrets at the organization level
so if you have secrets that are shared
across repos in your organization or in
your user maybe API keys that are used
by different pieces of software in your
organization or individually at the repo
level and also you can find
environments against your repo which
means that you can have an environment a
staging environment and a production
environment and you can say that this
workflow is running in this environment
and then it can perhaps access a
different version of secret depending on
which of the environments it's working
in so you might have a different API key
for development and production for
example that's why I love doing these
shows because I always learned something
I didn't know that good that's good
that's I've been trying with my head
around how to do something for someone
I'm working on at the moment if you go
to the settings as well as secrets and
things like that there's an environments
option and you can go in there and just
set up as many different environments
maybe I've just fed my imposter syndrome
some more thoughts there so do we know
where these actions or containers Run is
it on github's infrastructure or because
it's Microsoft Azure or something like
that do they tell us anything about that
I don't know that it's a secret I've
never looked into it in any detail so I
don't know is the honest answers as I
mentioned earlier I think they would
like you to think about it in a
serverless way it's just a container
that runs somewhere and you get some
results back do you know if there's an
option to run the container on one some
of your own stuff like a half on-prem
type solution I was just about to
mention that there is the option to run
a self-hosted runner do you want to
justifying a runner a runner is the
container that runs your workflow cool
yeah I'm familiar with that from
gitlab type yeah so you can again it's
one of these things that you can go into
your I think it's at your repo level you
can Define self-hosted Runners and they
give you a piece of software that you
then need to install on wherever you're
going to run stuff locally and that then
communicates with the GitHub
servers and does whatever GitHub wants
you to do yeah you can run GitHub
workflow Runners on your own Hardware if
you want and that'll pull down their
images and things like that two most
obvious reasons for doing that would be
security you have stuff you really don't
want to have running on github's servers
and secondly costs because they don't
charge you for running stuff on your own
hardware and I suppose yeah I mean that
what you mentioned before building your
own image to run your own jobs on means
that you know exactly what's in that
image as well so I've been doing a lot
of assures on supply chain security so
that would help validate and prove for
any
ISO regulations or bodies that you're
into say we're in full control yeah I
mean you say that but I've certainly
never built a Docker container that
hasn't been built on top of somebody
else's Docker container so that's worth
thinking about yeah normally you just
pulling something slim slim or you know
one of these ones that have
spent ages building all the different
bits that Pearl needs exactly no Elixir
needs or something like that okay that
almost finished off that section before
I move on to the example project the
runner is a good example that you can
just use their infrastructure but run it
on your new machine so then you're in
full control of
or secure a hardware resources you'll
need a good internet connection to pull
down the images the first time at least
yes okay so I'm gonna move on to the
last bit of our show I think we've done
a great exploration and definition of
GitHub actions which is the product name
then we've got the workflow that we're
in control of the file the ammo file and
then the actual keywords term actions
which is things we can use in the in the
GitHub actions Marketplace to run stuff
for us we then make a decision of
whether we want to use stock containers
or pulling our own whether we want to
run those on github's infrastructure and
potentially pay for that usage above and
beyond what we get for free or if we're
for example a violent core similar we
might want to use the the Free Runner
servers where we install a binary on our
own operating system and that pulls down
the images so let's scoop all that up
and go through project that you've
worked on or you've read about that
benefited from GitHub actions okay so if
you've got something in mind from that
we could there's a couple of things that
maybe we can talk about but I thought
maybe I mean we all hopefully understand
the CI CD thing so I think we might
touch on a couple of other uses
for it do you know the software
developer Simon Willison have you had
him on you should get him on at some
point I'll have a look he came up with a
concept he calls get scraping which is
powered by actions he has a piece of
software called Date which is good for
looking at Eskimo light databases and
git scraping is a way of building these
databases and what he does is he uses
the Cron job functionality for
triggering things and he'll find a
website that's got interesting data in
the form of a Json file and he will go
away and in the GitHub workflow he will
scrape that Json file and then use git
to do a diff between that and the
previous version and then he will well
obviously get will give him a history of
the changes in the data so I mean he's
doing things like he's talking about
websites that monitoring forest fires in
California and stuff like that and then
he can by taking the differences and
putting them in his sqlite database and
using his magic data set software it
builds websites that enable you to plot
that data on a graph or build various
interesting ways that data has changed
over time so that's I think is quite fun
and different use of GitHub actions I
guess basically you should realize that
what they're doing is GitHub are giving
you
free access to running Chrome tabs on
their servers so anything that you can
think of that is a scheduled do some
stuff and then store it either in GitHub
or in a database is something that you
can do from GitHub actions so you know
the sky's the limit there really another
thing I've done you mentioned right the
star that I was involved in the poll
community and so you know about cpan
some of your listeners might not realize
that cpan is the repository of free
Pearl libraries so add-on code for your
pill programs and the Pearl community in
cpan is very keen on they do a lot of
unit testing so I built a site called
cpan dashboard which anyone who writes
cpan modules can create a pull request
to my site adding them themselves to my
site and basically all we need is their
cpan username and then the site uses
GitHub actions to run some software
which pulls information about all of
their cpan modules from cpan so it uses
the meta cpan API and then produces a
list of all of their modules and oh they
also need to tell me which CI tools they
are using whether it's GitHub actions or
Travis Ci or Circle CI and it then goes
away on a schedule and interrogates all
of those services and builds badges
for all of those modules on all of the
CI services that that author uses so it
produces a rather nice visual
representation of all the modules that
the authors have written and how well
they are doing on the various CI
Services as a cpan author myself I use
that if I've got an afternoon where I
I've got nothing much to do I might go
and have a look at some of the patches
on that and see where my software can be
improved thanks Dave so just to
summarize because I want to go over an
example project that you discuss in your
book okay so building a static website
just to summarize these two examples
because I think they're a great showing
the completely two different ways to do
things the first one uses the Crone job
function of GitHub action so it goes off
and pairs a website does a different and
gets and then does the different things
that Simon wants to do I put up in a
link into the shootouts for anything
that you can give me about that too
and the second one is a site that you
run and collaboration with C partner
metacan where anyone can use the pull
request or an action in the GitHub
workflow file to run and trigger a few
different things based on the fact that
they Forge your repository and create a
pull request and then offer or go so
that will be a massive time saving for
you in the community as well yes
anything you can give me for the show
notes for that that would be great I
know it might be a simple project an
example project but just to scoop up
everything we've discussed for the sort
of last 15 minutes let's go through a
static website okay if we could
highlight the manual things you'd
normally do and then what you can do
with the GitHub actions touching on the
event you're going to use Secrets you're
going to have to think about whether
you're gonna have to access anything
else that isn't on GitHub and how you
manage that that would be great so yeah
aesthetic websites are in many ways
quite dull because you can actually do
that without GitHub actions at all I've
been dealing with what I call
semi-static websites which are a little
bit more more interesting if you
remember used to be quite popular in the
maybe 15 years ago the idea of a planet
website python had a piece of software
called planet planet which basically
what you do is you take RSS feeds web
feeds from various sources and you
aggregate them and you build a website
that is a basically a news page for a
particular topic maybe you're interested
in Doctor Who for example and there are
various websites that publish news about
Doctor Who and different stories will
appear during the day yeah so lately yes
once on postgres or any open source ones
yeah whatever you're looking at so I've
got a few sites that work like this so
basically you have a simple GitHub
workflow that mostly were on the Cron
job basis every three hours for example
it wakes up it pulls in
the RSS feeds from the half a dozen
websites that you're talking about it
then combines those RSS feeds into a new
RSS feed which it publishes and also
using probably the template toolkit
because I still use Perl for my a lot of
my personal stuff it will build an
index.html and publish that to a GitHub
GitHub website so it rebuilds the whole
thing every few hours but the other
thing that it does is this is obviously
driven from a configuration file it
could be a database but I use a
text-based configuration file which
lists all of the feeds that I'm
aggregating and obviously that might
change I might edit that add a new feed
or a feed has gone away so you delete it
or feeds move and stuff like that and so
it the
GitHub workflow definition has an on tag
which looks for pushes so a commit that
has been pushed to the repo but you can
further filter the push by saying
I want you to trigger for a push but
only when the push touches this
particular file so when the push
includes a change to the definition file
the config file then it fires and
rebuilds the website pulling in the new
feed or losing the old broken feed or
whatever that's exactly what I've been
looking for yeah yesterday I've got
projects I'm working on which is
about a new SAS thing that is particular
to my sector but it's got the marketing
web pages as part of the main site that
has all the API backend stuff so when I
make a front-end change to say a contact
page or a pricing page I don't really
want to run the whole test yeah and burn
through any minutes I've got or anything
like that so that's given me the perfect
idea to just say you know if anything in
these folders if that's an option
get touched then run the GitHub action
files so any of these triggers that fire
your workflow they all have various
types of filters on them yeah I thought
it was an all or nothing because it's
been giant Memento yeah sorry driving me
trying to think of well I don't want to
see that they are because I'm changing
this so that's and for the event
workflows so you've explained there that
there's a crown job that runs every
three hours to go off and fetch the RSS
feeds and then we'll commit to I presume
another repository which is the GitHub
Pages well actually no this is something
that I've taught myself recently because
it was causing me a problem GitHub Pages
can work in several different ways they
can serve the website from a different
branch or they can serve it from a slash
docs directory from the main branch or
from the root directory for things like
this where I've got some processing I
take the top the slash docs approach
where I've got all the code maybe in the
root directory and then it runs stuff
and it dumps the finished website into
the docs folder and then it commits that
new file from the docs folder into the
repo now that's a bit of a problem
because this is running around every
three hours committing a new version of
the index file and the new RSS feed file
so I found it causes a couple of
problems firstly it means that every
time that I go to my checkout of that
repo on my local disk I have to always
remember to start with a git pull
because there have been so many changes
since the last time I worked on that
file so I need to make sure that the
repo is up to date and secondly and this
might not be seen as a problem by by
some people but I was finding that a
couple of my repos were the most
committed GitHub repos in the UK for the
whole of of last year because it was
where they were running so many
automated commits and it's kind of cheap
because I'm not actually writing these
not that the number of GitHub commits
you do should be seen as a game of any
kind but it was like it was almost like
I was cheating at winning at the game
but it turns out that you don't actually
need to store the website that you've
built in the repo one of the things that
we haven't touched on because there's a
lot of GitHub action stuff we haven't
had time to touch on but one of the
things we haven't touched on is a thing
called artifacts so you can generate
what basically ends up as a zipped up
tarble it gets stored as an artifact on
GitHub servers and you can control how
long that artifact is kept for but
basically if you go to the web page
inside your repo for a GitHub workflow
run and it generated an artifact you can
download that artifact to your local
machine and examine it is that artifact
something that you've told it to gen
general term for there's a GitHub action
called build artifact or something like
that the W binary or something to deploy
or no that's we talked about the actions
earlier the libraries that you can use
within your workflow
that's one of these you just and you
just give it the path to the file or
files that you want to go in the zip
file can you give me an example of what
would be in there I use it for example
when you're when you're installing a
cpan module I mean this is probably true
for other languages as well if there are
errors it writes a log file but because
it's written that low file on your
container which is then ceased to exist
when the Run finishes if a module didn't
install successfully then you don't know
why it was broken you don't know what
went wrong so if you create an artifact
you say I talked earlier about
controlling the error flow and one of
the things you can do on an error is
take the log files and bundle them up
into an artifact this would be more
apparent because normally if something
fails and what I've experienced you can
go into the field job and expand the
debug logs and see it but I presume
that's only if you're spitting out the
logs to standard error or exactly you
know you're running a step by step to
get installer but if it's on your own
container or something and that's gone
yeah the logs aren't sparked out it gets
frustrating because it says installing
this module failed for full details see
this file and then it gives you a path
to a file that no longer exists you
create an artifact give it the path to
where you know that file is going to be
created and it bundles up any files it
finds stores those on GitHub servers and
you can then have a link to download
that artifact on the web page for that
run so you can download it and examine
it at your leisure so just going back to
this example project yes we've got a
Cron job definition to run let's say
every three hours
yeah you've got another event there that
runs something if you do a push to a
certain file because you've done that
level of granularity not just to push
the whole project which is how I've
always done it which I didn't even know
you could do which is amazing to learn
today can you have more definitions as
many as you want there yes like
granularity and you've also put the
artifact job on this project as well
yeah so you can have multiple keys under
the on command so in fact if you think
about it the job that you need to run
in the Cron job is regenerating the
website the job that you need to run
when the configuration file changes is
rebuild the website in exactly the same
way but when I tell it to because
there's an event that's triggered it so
the only thing that's different is the
is the way that it's triggered so for
these semi-static Planet files they
typically all have three keys in the on
trigger the Chron tab one if you've
changed the config file one which might
also because the other thing that might
change is I might tweak the template for
the index.html file the template that
generates the web page so obviously if I
change that I need to regenerate the
file as well
but also I will put in the workflow
dispatch key as well because I just want
to have that button appear that means I
can manually run it whenever I want
which often helps with debugging or
something like that that's helped me out
as well because I've also I've been in
the point where I've got a crime job
that runs a static code analysis on one
of my projects so when I make a commit I
have to wait till the next day to go
exactly see the results for some of it
yeah I didn't know about the dispatch
thing because I've always only rerun
them if you go into the action output
and click rerun all jobs or rerun field
jobs so that's great we've got three
different triggers but they all have the
same vect which means that I can put
them all in the same workflow definition
file which is just called
build.yaml or something like that just
there are three ways to trigger that
either there's a push on one of the
important files or it's a Cron job or I
just press the button and all three
three of those events have the same
action the same effect and they could
have
access to different Secrets at different
levels because you've clicked the button
you might have they could do yes yes I
mean there's all sorts of other things
you can do so you have as well as access
to Secrets you have access things called
contexts which is information about that
run and one of the context is the GitHub
context like a hash or a dictionary it's
called GitHub dot some and the dot
something will be the repo name or the
actor who's the name of the person who
triggered the run the actual GitHub
username the get reference that the
action is working on just all these
pieces of information information about
what actually triggered the run so you
can even though you've got the same
workflow that's triggered on three
different things one of the things that
you could look at within the GitHub
context is what the event was that
triggered so you can take different
actions if you want to okay is there a
difference
of what you can do if your repository is
a public one say because it's your
website or it's an open source project
versus a private one I haven't seen any
difference there's a difference in
pricing yeah I think you have to pay for
your own privacy for your private stuff
all the pricing is done on basically the
number of minutes of container time that
you use and as I've got a pro account so
within my private repos across all of my
private repos I get something like 3 000
minutes of free time every month and
anything over that it gets billed to me
and it's fractions of a penny per minute
thanks to going back to your example of
the three ways you could deploy a GitHub
static site I presume that might
possibly change your development process
because you've got these different
things that you can only access a
certain way is it something you need to
bear in mind when you're using GitHub
actions that things work a certain way
or it sounds like it's extremely
flexible given that I can't think of a
counter example I think all of my code
that I have written to run inside GitHub
actions is all completely
agnostic about the fact that it's
running inside a GitHub action if that
makes sense it's code that I can run
quite happily outside of GitHub access
it doesn't rely on anything in the
environment that it gets from GitHub
actions that stuff all of the GitHub
action stuff goes in the workflow
definition file not actually in the code
which I'm running so I don't thing I've
needed to change the way that I've
written software thanks I presume this
would just come down to the fact that
you remember you have to remember when
you're doing your testing you're not in
production so that's a separate thing
from what you can do yeah you just have
to do things a great way and use your
fixtures and your all sorts of different
stuff yes okay that finishes off the
example project
section nicely which was your planet
Cron job scrape RSS feeds every three
hours do something based on the push and
your artifacts which I think gave us a
nice overview of most of the different
parts of GitHub actions there's one
quick question that I think we've got
time for before I closes off it's a new
book and earlier on in the show you
talked about what you could do or you
mentioned when somebody raises an issue
you could do something what is that
there's a workflow where if somebody
opens an issue in your project yeah so
one of the triggers is I can't remember
what the name of the trigger is but you
get an issue raised and in that instance
the the GitHub context that I just
mentioned would be packed full of all
sorts of information about the issue
like the text of the issue and any tags
that has been been given oh so I'm just
going back to the context that's
potentially a set of environment
variables that you could pull on that's
specific to that instead of yeah
situation ah that makes more sense so
you could add other tag to the issue oh
one one nice thing that I've that I've
seen is you know things about the person
that raised the issue you can know
whether it's first time that this GitHub
user has raised an issue against this
project and you can send them a nice
welcoming email or add a comment to the
issue saying thank you welcome to the
project it's always nice to have new
people there's a few things that you can
do around that to just sort of
automatically welcome people into the
project
excellent thank you so yeah I think
we've done a great job of covering why
you should use our expand your use of
GitHub actions as you should do by
buying my book yeah exactly I'll make
sure there's a Link in the show notes
for that because I've enjoyed certain
reading through everything I've learned
so much more than good I thought I knew
anyway but now is the opportunity to
highlight
any one thing that you'd want a software
engineer to remember from our show can I
have two things right yeah one thing
that I think is worth mentioning is that
I know a lot of teams already have a lot
of resource invested in existing CI CD
Solutions they'll already have Duff in
circle Ci or Jenkins or something like
like that well GitHub have produced a
thing called the GitHub actions importer
which allows you to easily move your
workflows from a different system into
GitHub action so that's a good that's an
easy way to try things out
the main thing is CI and CD are great
and everyone should be using them but
GitHub action isn't just that as I said
earlier you have actions gives you
access to Containers running on GitHub
hardware and the sky really is the limit
in what you can do with it and I'd love
to hear about any interesting things
that people end up doing yeah there were
two great examples of
projects that I didn't think about with
the crown things so thank you for that
and you're my first guest that's ever
had two things in the section
so where can people find out more they
can follow you on Twitter which I've put
in the show notes is that what you
prefer or is there anywhere else to get
in touch yeah I'm on Twitter I'm also on
Mastodon on fossadon.org I think on most
social media I use the same tag which is
davorg d-a-v-o-r-g I'm even on that on
LinkedIn so if anybody wants to password
based me on LinkedIn if they want to
talk about more professional things then
maybe that's the appropriate place
thanks Dave thank you for coming on the
show it's been a real pleasure it's been
a pleasure this is Gavin Henry for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]